Well, I guess we'll wade into this
religiosity again. Nutrition. There's
this huge study that's been making the
rounds across the social media
landscape. And as you can see by the
title, we're just dis we're discussing
the nutrition patterns linked to healthy
aging. In this study, which was a
long-term observational study including
over 100,000 participants over 30 years,
the researchers quantified how many
people were still considered aging in a
healthy manner according to five
criteria. The criteria were one if
people survived to 70, two if people
were free of 11 major diseases from type
two diabetes, cardiovascular disease,
cancer to autoimmune diseases, multiple
sclerosis, arthritis and more. Uh three
if people were had intact cognitive
function, four if people had intact
physical function, and five if people
had intact mental health. Then
researchers looked at people's diets
every four years via validated food
frequency questionnaires. That means
that the researchers asked general
questions about average intake of
particular foods like over the past year
how often on average do you consume X?
So typically people will have some
general idea of what they consume. If
you're a person on a low carb diet, you
can answer a question about pasta pretty
well. And if I were asked about quinoa,
I know to answer, "Not once in the last
year," as I stare disgustedly at the
researcher. But the researchers also
validated these questionnaires using
dietary records, biomarker measures, and
some other validation techniques to
verify the consistency and accuracy of
the collection. So before we go on,
let's pause for a second for people who
don't know anything about nutritional
epidemiology to post their comment about
how food frequency questionnaires are
nonsense. Oh, relax. I'm just needling
you. Just a joke. Don't crucify me,
please. Okay. Okay. I'm sorry. All
knowing one. We
cool. Let's look into uh some of the
results. We have the uh various diets on
the left side. Don't worry, we'll get
into more specifics on them later. Just
uh know that they're different diet
categories. The very right side is a
heat map of the relative odds of each
diet compared against each other. So for
example, the
AHI 2010 diet pattern compared against
the REIP diet is green, which with an
asterisk, which indicates that the
AHI 2010 diet is statistically
significantly better for healthy aging
than the reedip diet. If it were red, it
would be worse, but you'd have to sit
there and analyze it for some time. So
the researchers also indicated the odds
ratio. That's the O at the bottom there
of healthy aging within each diet as
well. That means that comparing those
that are in the lowest adherence to that
of a particular diet pattern versus
those that have the highest adherence.
If the dots and lines move to the right,
that's higher odds of healthy aging.
You'll notice that all the diets
indicate improvement in healthy aging
with some maybe slightly edging out
others, which is why the heat map
exists. The overall point here is that
the commonalities between these diets
allows for better odds of healthy aging
if a person is more adherent. Okay. Then
the question is what are the trends in
these diets that indicate improved odds
of healthy
aging? Joy. Oh joy, we get to look at
another heat map. The main outcome is
the one on the far left, healthy aging.
Still, if you want to break it up by
component of healthy aging, those are
also shown. Then we have a
long list of different types of foods on
the left side. I'm not going to lecture
going over each food by food as you can
read it for yourself, but let's
highlight a few. Remember, if it's
green, it indicates that the more of
that food or nutrient, the association
in favor of healthy aging. If it's red,
it's an inverse association. The more of
it, the link is worse aging. If there's
a star in the box, that's a
statistically significant result. So
near the top as having a positive
relationship with healthy aging are
things like fruit, consuming more
unsaturated fats than saturated fats,
whole grains, vegetables, and the list
goes on, including the dreaded seed oils
further down. On the other hand, more
trans fats, more meats, more sodium, and
more processed meats are linked to worse
odds of healthy aging as previously
defined. Now, in typical partisan
fashion, some people will be extremely
happy about these results and another
group will be extremely unhappy. So, let
me speak to the reasonable middle since
uh we've lost a big chunk of people. Uh
there are some puzzling aspects about
these data. For example, looking at fast
and fried food in the middle there, I
tried to find some explanation for this
result. Uh why would fried food and fast
food be linked to healthy aging? The
researcher's explanation is that this is
a measure of going out for fast food
which indicates a social impact as in
going out to eat is linked to better
overall social relationships which
contribute to a more vibrant life. You
know, when you chew gum and then you
pull on it and it stretches out
massively. If the gum were the
explanation given here, uh, they're
stretching it. No doubt there might be a
social impact, but that it would
overcome the negative effects of fast
food and fried food seems just
absolutely absurd to me. I think there's
likely something else going on here that
just isn't being explored. I'd also add
that things like coffee, seafood, and
tea, which have a great track record for
cognitive benefit, were either linked to
worse or neutral cognitive function.
Some of this might be explained by the
group that they sampled, so nurses and
other health professionals. It's
possible that coffee and tea consumption
were heightened at unhealthy times, so
night shifts and so forth. Just a guess,
though. So, no doubt there's some
puzzling relationships here in the
middle.
and beer being linked to worse mental
health. Come on, man. Now you've crossed
the
line. I suppose I should also mention
that these associations aren't simple
associations, but they are adjusted for
covariants, meaning that the researchers
are controlled for possible influencing
factors. So here's a list. Now, what
about ultrarocessed foods? Before that,
the researchers did further subgroup
analyses to find out if certain people
like those that are physically active or
those that aren't overweight along with
other subgroups if these groups
experience more or less benefit from
these dietary patterns. I'll be covering
that and more in the extended version of
this video that you're watching, which
is part of the Physionic Insiders. Along
with that, you get access to my full
library of study investigations along
with summaries, a private podcast, live
sessions with yours truly. Uh, if you're
still upset about the jokes that I gave
earlier, then well, unfortunately, you
probably will suffer double as an
insider. But for the rest of you, I hope
to see you there. Well, on the uh
ultrarocessed food front, even with all
the adjustments across the board, they
were linked to worse odds of healthy
aging. Now, some more on these diets.
Here are their diet names. Now, I'm not
going to go through every single diet
and list out all of their components.
But I will tell you some of the
commonalities across them. All of them
without exception focused on plant-based
foods like whole grains, fruits,
vegetables, nuts, uh legumes, as well as
incorporated tea and coffee. On the
other hand, they deemphasized red meat,
refined grains, uh fried foods, butter,
sugary drinks, saturated fats, and
sodium. I did find this a bit
disappointing because the similarity
between these diets except for small
nuances really just seems to repeat the
same point. In one way, you could
consider that a good thing, but I would
like to see greater differences between
diets to really tease out some of the
true comparisons between divergent
diets. Also, it's not like participants
specifically consumed these diets. They
were segregated based on their collected
dietary records to fit these named diet
patterns based on the score which they
were then fit into each group. So that
might explain why the diets are
relatively similar. I'm really not sure.
Okay, I've said this before, but I know
that people often mention that when they
avoid certain plant-based foods, they
feel better or they get better results.
Well, two things. One, this study
doesn't directly compare against
specifically non-plant-based diets. Two,
these expansive studies inform on
overall trends on how a person should
think about structuring their diet, but
it doesn't consider individual
circumstances. Some people will have bad
reactions to certain foods or certain
dietary patterns. In that case, your
priority on what to eat changes and
likely doesn't reflect what the studies
like this indicate. This analysis isn't
a condemnation of your personal
experience. It's merely a speaking on
the whole if possible. And if you care
about healthy aging, going plantforward
is associated with better health
according to this analysis. So, the main
points here are that when adjusting for
many influencing factors, likely
plant-based nutrition styles are
associated with healthy aging, although
direct comparisons with non-plant-based
or particularly low carbohydrate diets
was not made. If I haven't completely
alienated you at this point, I'd love to
continue to try in this next video.
Thanks for tuning in.